The following content is provided under a Creative
Commons license.
Your support will help MIT OpenCourseWare continue to
offer high quality educational resources for free.
To make a donation or view additional materials from
hundreds of MIT courses, visit MIT OpenCourseWare at
ocw.mit.edu.
Who can tell me what a proof is?
Any ideas of what is a proof anyway?
Any thoughts?
Yeah?
Very good.
I like that.
That's very close to what we're going to do here.
Yeah?
Now that's a special kind of proof, though.
That's a mathematical proof.
And I'm going to write a definition very close to that
in a few minutes.
But proofs exist beyond mathematics.
Can anybody think of a higher level notion of what a
proof is?
That's correct what you said, but there's a higher metal
level notion of what a proof is.
Beyond that, may have no logical deductions potentially.
May have no assumptions.
Any thoughts?
Got a proof?
Well, I think generally a proof is considered across
multiple fields as a method for
ascertaining the truth.
And you described one method.
Now by ascertaining, I mean establishing truth,
verifying truth.
And there's lots of ways to ascertain truth in society and
even within science.
What are some examples of ways that we
ascertain truth in society?
Yeah?
Observation.
Experiment and observation.
Excellent.
That's the bedrock of physics.
I mean, who really knows if there's gravity out there?
Well, we observe it.
And so we then conclude that's the truth.
There's gravity and we have laws about it.
That's one good way.
What's another way of ascertaining truth across
scientific disciplines or in science, beyond
science just in society?
How is truth established?
What are the ways?
What things aren't true and that helps you narrow
down what is true?
Yes, truth?
Yeah, that's great.
Truth is the opposite of falsehood.
How do we establish falsehood?
What are the ways of doing that?
How do you decide something is not true?
In everyday life, yeah.
Find counter examples.
Yeah, that's good.
So in fact, even a step more general sampling,
counter examples are ways.
You know, if you do something and experiment 10 times
and every time it comes out one way,
that's truth, maybe.
But there's fields where that becomes truth.
What about other ways?
How are we going to decide if Roger Clemens
is guilty of perjury for lying about
steroids to Congress?
He did it or he didn't.
How are we going to decide that?
What's the truth behind it?
How is that truth going to be ascertained?
Yeah?
Examining evidence and who makes the conclusion there?
The jury.
Truth is established by juries or judges.
You know, Blago, I can never pronounce his name.
Illinois Governor, Blago Djavic, he's guilty.
That's the truth.
Okay?
Of, you know, not of conspiracy,
trying to sell Obama's Senate seat,
but of lying to the authorities about campaign financing.
O.J. is guilty, not of killing his wife,
but of breaking into an apartment
to steal back some of his merchandise.
Okay?
So judges and juries make decisions on truth.
What are other truths, bigger truths even
than judges and juries in society?
There's one really big one that causes a lot of issues, yeah?
Religion.
What is it?
Religion, the word of God.
Broadly construed here.
Or religion.
You know?
Now that one's really hard to argue about.
You know, because you believe it.
You know?
And especially if you're not talking to God regularly
and somebody is, well, it's hard to argue about,
you know, the truth.
So you rely on others to interpret it for you often.
You know, a priest or minister or rabbi.
Okay?
And it gets complicated because you can end up
with conflicting truths based on, you know,
who you think you're talking to
or who your translator is for you.
You know, another one is the word of your boss.
Whatever the boss says is right.
Often in business, the customer is always right.
That's the truth, whatever the customer says.
All right?
You know, with Donald Trump as your boss,
you better agree or you're fired, right?
Often in classes, the professor says it is true
because the authority said it.
That's not true here.
All right?
That will not hold.
And one of the nicest things about math that I like a lot
is that the youngest student can stand up against
the most, oldest, most experienced professor
and win an argument on mathematics.
In fact, I really do get pleasure
when a student comes up and proves me wrong.
I loved it when that student came in and she showed me
what I said really wasn't right
when you looked at it carefully or in a different light.
You know, now, sometimes if I do it on the board here
and it's in class, well, you know, that's fun.
I feel a little embarrassed afterwards,
but it's a good thing about mathematics
is that you can have that kind of dialogue.
Okay.
Another one, which is related to the word of God sometimes,
is inner conviction.
Very popular in computer science, believe it or not.
You know, with the mantra,
there are no bugs in my program.
Can't tell you how many times, you know, you hear that.
Closely related is I don't see why not.
Something is true.
And that's a good one because that transfers the burden
of proof to anybody who disagrees with you.
You don't have to prove it to say,
I don't see why it's not true.
All of a sudden, the other person who's questioning you
becomes their job to disprove you,
which is not so good.
Okay.
Now, in mathematics, there's this higher level
and someone stated it very clearly up there.
Let me write it up here.
In mathematics, we have a mathematical proof,
is a verification of a proposition
by a chain of logical deductions
from a set of axioms.
Now, that's a bit of a mouthful.
There's three important components here.
Propositions, logical deductions, and axioms.
And we're going to spend the rest of the class today
talking about each of these
and then give an example of a proof.
We'll start with propositions.
A proposition is a statement
that is either true or false.
You may not know which one,
but it's one or the other.
Simple example, 2 plus 3 equals 5.
Now, that's a true proposition.
Here's one that's a little more interesting.
For all n in the set of natural numbers,
n squared plus n plus 41 is a prime number.
Now, I've used some notation here.
This is the upside down a is the for all symbol.
How many people have not seen that symbol before?
I had a bunch of you.
You're going to see a bunch of symbols here first week.
And that means for every possible choice of n,
and this is in the natural numbers,
which is the set, 0, 1, 2, 3, and so forth.
It's the natural numbers.
It's basically the integers, but not negative.
So we're saying for every natural number,
i.e. for 0, for 1, for 2, for 3, and so forth,
this expression is a prime.
Now, a prime number is a number that is not divisible
by any other number besides itself in one.
So 2, 3, 5, 7, or prime, 9 is not because it's 3 times 3.
Now, this part here is called the predicate.
And a predicate is a proposition whose truth depends
on the value of a variable, in this case n.
This is referred to as the universe of discourse.
It's the space of all things we're talking about.
We're only talking about natural numbers here.
This is called a quantifier.
We'll see more quantifiers later.
All right, now to see if this proposition is true,
we need to make sure that this predicate
is true for every natural number n.
So let's see if we can check that.
Let's try some values.
So we'll try n is 1, 2, 3, and so forth.
And we'll compute n squared plus n plus 41.
And then we'll check, is it prime?
So for n equals 0, n squared plus n plus 41 is 41.
Is 41 prime?
Yeah, nothing divides 41 but itself in one.
All right, let's try 1.
1 squared plus 1 plus 41 is 43.
43 prime.
Yes.
Let's try 2.
We've got 4 plus 2 is 6 plus 41.
47.
Is 47 prime?
Yes.
Looking good.
3, I got 9, 12, 53.
53 prime?
Yeah.
And I could keep on going here.
I could go down to 20.
I get 420, 461.
In fact, that is a prime.
And I could just keep on going here.
Go down to 39.
I get 1,601.
You can check that as a prime.
The first 40 values of n, the proposition is true.
The predicate is true.
It is prime.
Now, this is a great example because in a lot of fields,
physics, for example, statistics often,
if it's true, you checked 40 examples.
That's above and beyond the call of duty.
It's always true.
So yeah, this must be true, right?
No.
Wrong.
Often you'll see this in a lot of scientific fields.
It is not true.
Can anybody give me an example of n
for which n squared plus n plus 41 is not prime?
Yeah.
40.
Good.
Let's see about 40.
40 squared plus 40 plus 41 is 1681.
What's that equal?
41 squared.
So it is not prime.
Somebody give me an obvious example where it's not prime.
41.
Yeah, 41 squared.
Everything is divided by 41.
But 40 is the first break point.
So the first 40 examples work and then it fails.
So this proposition is false,
even though it was looking pretty good.
There's a reason I'm doing this effect.
I'm going to do it some more here.
I'm going to beat you over the head with it.
Here's a famous in mathematics statement.
A to the fourth plus B to the fourth
plus C to the fourth equals D to the fourth
has no positive integer solutions.
That is a proposition.
Now, this proposition was conjectured to be true
by Euler in 1769.
Euler's a big honcho in math.
We still talk about him a lot,
even though he's been dead for centuries.
It was unsolved for over two centuries.
Mathematicians worked on it.
It was finally disproved by a very clever fellow
named Noam Elkes.
218 years later, after it was conjectured,
he works at that other school down the street.
And he came up with this.
A equals 95,800.
B equals 217,519.
C equals 414,560.
You don't have to remember these numbers.
We're not going to quiz you on that.
422,481.
Now, he claims I've never personally checked it,
but presumably people have.
You plug those in here and you have an equality.
So he says.
So in fact, the correct true proposition is
there do exist A, B, C, D
in the positive natural numbers
such that A to the fourth plus B to the fourth
plus C to the fourth equals D to the fourth.
All right, I used a new quantifier here
called there exists.
Instead of an upside down A, it's a backwards E.
Don't ask me why.
That's what it is.
The plus means you can't have
zero or negative numbers.
So these are the positive natural numbers.
And here's your predicate,
which of course the truth of this depends
on the values of A, B, C, and D.
All right, it took a long time to figure out
that actually there was a solution here.
Obviously everything they tried to let time failed.
Let me give you another one.
313 x cubed plus y cubed
equals z cubed
has no positive integer solutions.
This turns out to be false,
but the shortest, smallest counter example
has over a thousand digits.
This one was easy.
They only have six digits.
So there's no way ever you'd use a computer
to exhaustively search a thousand digit numbers here
to show it's false.
Now of course some of you are probably thinking
why on earth would I care
if 313 x cubed plus y cubed equals z cubed
has a solution?
Now that probably won't be the last time
that thought occurs to you during the term.
And why on earth would anybody
ever try to even find a solution to that?
You know, I mean mathematicians are sort of a rare breed.
Now actually in this case
that's really important in practice.
This equation is an example
of what's called an elliptic curve.
Elliptic curve and you study these
if you're really a specialist in mathematics
in graduate school
or if you work for certain three letter agencies
because it's central to the understanding
of how to factor large integers.
That means factoring,
showing that what was it?
1681 is 41 x 41.
And I said okay, who cares about factoring?
Well factoring is the way
to break crypto systems like RSA
which are used for everything
that we do electronically today.
You have a PayPal account,
you buy something online, you're using SSL.
They're all using crypto systems
most of which are almost all
which are based on number theory.
And in particular, they're based on factoring.
And if you can find good solutions
to things like this
or solutions to things like this
all of a sudden you can get
an angle and a wedge on factoring.
And it's because of that
that now RSA uses
thousand digit
modelluses instead of
hundred digit modelluses like they used to use
because people figured out how to factor them
and how to break the crypto system.
If you can break those crypto systems
you can't rule the world
but it's close.
So you'll learn, we'll talk more about this
the week after next when we do number theory
and we work up to RSA
and how that crypto system works
and why factoring is so important.
So you all don't have to
really have to worry about this
but these things are important.
And the bigger message is
that you don't just try a few cases
and if it works you think it's done.
That's not
how the game works in mathematics.
You can get an idea of maybe it's true
but it doesn't tell you the answer.
All right, let me give it another one.
This is another very famous one
that probably most of you have heard of.
The regions
in any map
can be colored
in four colors
so that
adjacent regions
have different colors.
Like a map of the United States
every state gets a color
two states share a border
they have different colors
as you can distinguish them.
This is known as the four color theorem
and it's very famous
in the popular literature.
How many people have heard of this theorem before?
Yeah, okay, so you've all heard of it.
As a long history
it was conjectured by somebody named Guthrie
in 1853.
He's the first person to say this ought to be possible.
And there were many
false proofs
over the ensuing century.
One of the most
convincing was a proof using pictures
by Kempe in 1879.
You know, 26 years later.
And this proof was
believed for over a decade.
Mathematicians thought the proof was right
until another mathematician named He-Wood
found a fatal flaw
in the argument.
Now this proof
by Kempe consisted of drawing pictures
of what maps have to look like.
You start by saying a map
has to look like one of these types.
And he would draw pictures of them.
And then he argued that those types
that he drew pictures of it worked for it.
Proofs by picture
are often very convincing
and very wrong.
And I'm going to give you one
to start lecture next time.
Be proof by PowerPoint, which is even worse
than proof by picture.
And it is compelling.
You know.
The point will be to show you proofs by picture
are generally not a good thing.
Because your brain just locks in.
That's what it has to look like.
And you don't think about other ways
that it might look like.
Now the four color theorem was finally proved
by Oppel and Hocken
in 1977.
But they had to use a computer
to check thousands of cases.
Now
this was a little disturbing
to mathematicians because
how do they know the computer did the right thing?
You know
your colleague writes a proof on the board.
You can check it. But how do you know
the computer didn't mess up or not do some cases?
Now
everybody believes it's true now.
But it's unsatisfying.
A few years ago
a 12 page human proof was discovered.
But it's not been verified.
And people are very suspicious of it
because the proof of the main lemma
says, quote
details of this lemma
is left to the reader, C figure 7.
That's what the main lemma
of the proof is. But people think
there maybe were some good ideas there.
But very suspicious proof.
Alright.
Let's do another one.
Another proposition.
Also very famous.
Every even integer
but 2
actually positive integer
is the sum
of 2 primes.
For example
24 is the sum of 11 and 13
which are prime.
Anybody know is this true or false?
This proposition.
Yeah?
Yeah, that's right. Me too.
Nobody knows
if this is true or false.
This is called
Golbach's conjecture.
It was conjectured by
Christian Golbach in 1742.
This is a really
simple proposition.
And it's amazing
it's not known. In fact I spent
a couple of years working on
I thought this has to be easy enough to prove
when I was younger.
And didn't get very far.
So people still don't know if it's true.
And in fact it was listed
by the globe
as one of the great unsolved mysteries.
So if you get out this globe article here
on the handout. Does everybody have this handout?
If you don't
we'll get it passed out. Somebody missing that handout
up over there and over here.
If we get those passed out.
Now it lists the three conjectures.
Do you see Golbach's conjecture there?
Now can anybody
point out something
that's a little disturbing about
what the globe says about
Golbach's conjecture?
Yeah. It gives the example
instead of 24 is 11 plus 13
it says 20
is the sum of 9 and 11.
Now
if we're allowed to use things like
9 as primes, Golbach's conjecture
is pretty easy to prove. It's true.
This won't be the last time
we get examples from the literature.
In fact we're going to do this a lot.
Along this theme of you cannot believe
everything you read.
Now the globe is easy pickings but we'll do
some more interesting ones later.
Now this article lists two other famous conjectures
which most people believe to be true.
The Riemann Hypothesis
after a 1859 paper
written by Bernard Riemann
suggests that zeros
in an infinite series of numbers known as a zeta function
form along a straight line in the complex plane.
The hypothesis has been proved
to 1.5 billion zeros.
Not far enough to prove it
completely.
If they did 1.5 trillion zeros
it wouldn't be far enough to prove it completely, of course.
And then
the
the Riemann Hypothesis
a couple of years ago
somebody credible claimed to have proved it
proved turned out not to be right.
Then there's the Poincare conjecture.
Now this one was
finished off.
It was proved to be true in 2003
by a Russian named Grigor Perlman.
The conjecture says
roughly speaking that
3D objects without
holes, like not a donut
are equivalent
to the sphere. They can sort of be deformed
into a sphere.
This is known to be true in four dimensions
and higher but nobody could prove it for three dimensions
until Perlman came along.
Now there's a bit of a controversy around this guy.
He had an 80 page proof
but didn't have all the details.
So then other teams of mathematicians got together
and wrote 350 pages
of details
and then most people believe now
that it's right and that his original proof
might not have had all the details
but he had the right structure of the proof.
So he won prizes
for this. He won the highest prize
in mathematics, the Fields Medal
and just earlier this year
he was awarded the 1 million dollar
Millennium Prize and there's about
six problems or so that if you solve one
of them the Clay Institute gives you a million
dollars and he's the first one
to win the million dollars.
Now the guy's a little strange.
He rejected the Fields Medal and refused
to go to the ceremony where he was being honored
and he's recently rejected the Millennium Prize.
In any way
this area is murky and we have an expert
to explain it all
for us on video which I thought I'd show.
Alright let's do
a simpler one here.
For all n
in z
n greater than or equal to 2
implies
n squared greater than or equal to 4.
Now z
we use for the integers
and so that would be
0, 1, minus 1, 2,
minus 2 and so forth
and this symbol
here is
implies.
Alright in fact
one thing you can notice when you read the text
is we use different notation
there as the standard
that I will use in lecture
and there's lots of ways of doing it.
You could have a double arrow, a single arrow
you could write out implies every time
as done in the text and it doesn't really
matter which one you want to use
as long as you use one of the conventions
for implies.
And let me define what
implies means.
An implication
p implies q
is
said to be true
if
p is false
or q
is true
either one.
So we can write this down in terms of a truth table
as follows
we have the values of p and q
and I'll give the value of p implies q
if p is q
and q is true
sorry p is true and q is true
what about p implies q?
It's true because q is true
the definition
if p is true and q is false
false
p is false
q is true
what about false and false
is true
even though
this is false as long as p is false
p implies q is true
so this is important to remember
false implies anything
is true
which is a little
strange there's a famous expression
if pigs could fly
I would be king
is that true?
In fact this statement
pigs fly
implies
I'm king
that's true
because pigs don't fly
it doesn't matter whether or not I'm king
which I'm not
since pigs don't fly
even though that's false
the implication is true
now some of you have worked on these things before
second nature if you haven't
want to start getting familiar
with that
alright let's do another example
what about this proposition
for all n for all integers
n and z
n greater than or equal to 2
this is if and only if
n squared greater than or equal to 4
is that true
is n bigger than 2 if and only
if n squared is bigger than 4
it's false
what's an example of n for which that's false
negative
alright so it's false
n equals negative
alright
negative 3 squared is bigger than or equal to 4
but negative 3 is not bigger than or equal to 2
and in fact
this if and only if means
you have to have an implication
both ways
so you got to check both ways
for it so let's do the truth table
extend this truth table out here
to do the truth table for p
if and only if q
alright so here
p and q
is q implies p
true for this row
does q imply
true imply true
yeah
false implies true
that's true
true does not imply false that's false
and false implies false
and so now we can see
where p
is if and only if q
if they're both
true
then it's true here
what about here is p true if and only if q is true
in this case
no
because p implies q is false
but q implies p is true
so it's false
false here
I made a mistake there right
that was true
and true
if and only if true
they're both true so we're okay
so p if and only if q
is true when they're both true
or both false
that's it
they're different then it's not true
the key here is to always check
both ways
so if you're asked to prove an if and only if
you got to prove that way
and that way
alright we've just done about 15 propositions
is every sentence
a proposition?
yes? no?
no what's an example of something that's not a proposition
a what?
this statement is false
that's true
it's not a proposition
because if it were true
it wouldn't be false and if it was false
then it would be true and you have a contradiction
so it's neither true nor false
what's a more simple example of something that's not a proposition
boy I would have said that's true
in some some world
you know because that yeah that's a tissue
so it's a true statement
hello
that's good that's neither true nor false
yeah a question
who are you?
neither true nor false so not everything
is a proposition but this course pretty much everything we deal with
will be a proposition
alright so
that's it for propositions
any questions on propositions?
alright next we're going to talk about
axioms
now
the good news is that axioms are the same thing
really is propositions
the only difference is that
axioms are propositions
that we just assume are true
an axiom
is a proposition
that is assumed
to be true
there's no proof
that an axiom is true
you just assume it
because you think it's reasonable
in fact the word axiom comes from
greek it doesn't mean
to be true
it means to think worthy
something you think is worthy enough to be assumed
to be true
now a lot of times you hear people say
sometimes we'll even say it to you
you know don't make assumptions when you're doing math
no
that's not true
you have to make assumptions when you do math
otherwise you can't do anything
because you got to start with some axioms
the key in math
is to identify
what your assumptions are so people can see them
and the idea is
that when you do a proof
anybody who agrees with your assumptions
or your axioms
can follow your proof and they have to agree with your conclusion
now they might disagree
with your axioms in which case they're not going to buy your
proof
now there are lots of axioms used in math
for example
if a equals
b
and b equals c
then
a equals c
there is no proof of that
but it seems pretty good
and so we just throw it in the bucket of
axioms and use it
now
axioms can be contradictory in different
context
here's a good example
in Euclidean geometry
there's a central axiom
that says
given
a line
l
and a point
p
not on l
there is
exactly one line
through p
parallel to l
you all saw this in geometry
in middle school right
at a point in a line there's exactly one line
another line through the point that's parallel to the line
now there's also a field
called spherical geometry
and there you have an axiom
that contradicts this
it says given a line l and a point p
not on l
there is no
line
through p parallel to l
on the sphere
there's a field called
hyperbolic
geometry
and there
there's an axiom that says given a line l
and a point p not on l
there are
infinitely many
lines through p parallel to l
so how can this be
does that mean one of these fields is totally bogus
or two of them are
because they've got contradictory axioms
that's okay
just whatever field you're in
state your axioms
and they do make sense
in their various fields
you know this is planar geometry
this is on the sphere and this is on
hyperbolic geometry
they make sense in those contexts
so you can have
more or less whatever axioms you want
there are sort of two guiding principles
to axioms
axioms should be
it's called consistent
and complete
now
a set of axioms
is consistent
if no proposition
can be proved to be both
true and false
and you can see why that's important
you know if you spend three weeks
proving something's true
and the next day somebody proves it's also
false
I mean the whole thing was pointless
so it only makes sense if your axioms as a group
are consistent
a set of axioms
is said to be complete
if it can be used
to prove
every proposition
is either true or false
alright
now this is desirable because it means
well you can solve every problem
alright everything is
you can prove it's true
or you can prove it's false
you can get to the end
now you'd think it shouldn't be too hard
to get a set of axioms that satisfies
these two basic properties
you're allowed to choose whatever you want
really just you don't want to
be creating contradictions
and you want a set that's powerful enough
that allows you to prove everything is true or false
one of the two
turned out not to be so easy to do this
in fact
many logicians spent their careers
famous logicians trying to
find a set of axioms
just one set that was
consistent and complete
in fact Russell and Whitehead are probably
the two most famous
they spent their entire careers doing this
and they never got there
then one day this guy named Kurt Gertl
showed up
and in the 1930s
he proved it's not possible
that there exist any set of axioms
that are both consistent
and complete
now this discovery devastated
the field
it was a huge discovery
you know imagine
poor Russell and Whitehead
they spent their entire careers
going after this holy grail
then Kurt shows up and said hey guys there's no grail
doesn't exist
and that's a little depressing
pretty bad day when that happened
now it's an amazing result
because it says if you want consistency
and that's a must
there will be true facts
that you will never be able to prove
we're not going to prove that here
it's proved in a logic course
for example maybe Goldback's conjecture
is true
and it is impossible to prove
now we're going to try
not to assign any of those problems for homework
and in fact people
they do exist it's complicated
you can state a problem
that you can't prove is true or false
and you may be thinking that from time to time
hey it's one of those
you remember
what your parents told you
if you work hard enough
you can do anything
they were wrong
alright that's enough for now
we'll do more of this next time